So, today's דף daf is קמ"א Kuf Mem Aleph 141, we pick
up on the bottom of ק"מ Kuf Mem at the
משנה. mishnah. גורפין מלפני הפטם ומסלקין לצדדים. Gorfin milifnei hapatam umesalkin litzdadim.
You can sweep away the like the dung from in front of
an ox that's being fattened, a cow that's being fattened, because basically
you don't want him to walk
into you don't want him to walk into this stuff.
Okay,
right, I'm sorry, right, רש"י Rashi says not necessarily sweeping the dung.
But anyway, רש"י Rashi says you can sweep in front of him
because you're going to be placing you're going to be placing like
the straw for him in front of him for him to eat
and you don't want it to get dirty or whatever, so you
can sweep the area in front of the cow that you are
fattening.
ומסלקין לצדדים מפני הראי. Umesalkin litzdadim mipnei hare'i.
Now if you can also move this move this the straw to
the side
so that he does not sort of somehow get it mixed up
with his dung and
and get the straw inedible and dirty. So again, I'm not exactly
sure of the
exact מציאות metzius here about fattening cows and so on, but the
basic point is is that you can move the straw and sweep
the straw away in order so that or sweep the area in
front of the straw and move the straw away so that things
don't get dirty. דברי רבי דוסא. Divrei Rabbi Dosa. That's what רבי
דוסא Rabbi Dosa says. וחכמים אוסרין. Vachachamim osrin. And the rabbis forbid
it and we'll see on which this is referring to and why
they forbid this. נוטלין מלפני בהמה זו ונותנין לפני בהמה זו בשבת.
Notlin milifnei behema zu venotnin lifnei behema zu beShabbat. You can also
remove food from in front of one animal and put it in
front of another animal. And now obviously that should be obvious if
you can feed an animal why can't you remove food from one
and put it in front of another? But you might think that
once one animal started eating from it, the other animal wouldn't want
to eat from the same food, so maybe at that point it
would become no longer fit, it would be a type of a
מוקצה, muktzah, and tells you that's not a problem. Okay, so clearly
herbivores. What? Clearly herbivores that they'll eat each other's food.
Right, carnivores won't you know let anybody.
Okay, so right, well these that's what it is, these are basically
cows, farm animals. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. They raised the question. רבנן ארישא פליגי או
אסיפא פליגי. Rabbanan areisha pligi o aseifa pligi. When the rabbis argue,
do they argue in the first case, sweeping the area in order
to in order to put it to put the grain on the
ground, or do they argue on the second part which is getting
the straw out of the way so it doesn't get mixed up
with dung? או אתרווייהו פליגי. O atravayhu pligi. Or maybe they argue
on both cases. תא שמע. Ta shema. Come and hear a ברייתא.
braita. וחכמים אומרים אחד זה ואחד זה לא יסלקנו לצדדים. Vachachamim omrim
echad ze ve'echad ze lo yesalkenu litzdadim. Whether the first case or
the second case, you should not move it to the side. Okay,
we have yet to see exactly what the concern is exactly. And
take a look at רש"י Rashi four lines down in the wide
lines, he tells you what the possible concerns is. רש"י Rashi says
where it says פליגי, pligi, he says גורפין, gorfin, on sweeping the
area in front of where you're going to put down the
grain, דבשייף הכרקא וכמחזי להשווי גומות. deshayef hakarka vekamichaze lehashvei gumot. If
you sweep, if you're dealing with dirt, a dirt floor, and not
like a and not like a a wooden or other type of
a trough, then by sweeping you're going to smooth the floor, and
that's a type of a בונה. boneh. So basically that's the reason
not to allow the sweeping in front of the trough and where
you're going to put the food. That's one concern. Okay,
and then או אסיפא פליגי, o aseifa pligi, the next רש"י, Rashi,
משום דלא חזי שיש בה שמץ משום רגליו, mishum dela chazi sheyesh
bah shemetz mishum raglav, because maybe the problem in the second case
is that when you're sweeping away the grain after he's eaten it
and after he's walked on it, maybe it's already מוקצה muktzah and
it's no longer fit. So those are the two reasons to be
concerned: smoothing the ground or the grain not becoming fit. And we
see from the ברייתא braita that the rabbis argue on both. אמר
רב חסדא מחלוקת באבוס של קרקע. Amar Rav Chisda machlokes be'evus shel
karka. And now you see where רש"י Rashi is getting it: the
whole debate is if it is out of dirt, it's a dirt
floor. Okay, because then it's a problem like smoothing the ground. אבל
באבוס של כלי. Aval be'evus shel kli. But if it's a type
of a trough that's out of a vessel, some type of a
wood or other type of a trough, דברי הכל מותר, divrei hakol
mutar, it's not a problem, what are you doing? You're just sweeping
it out. So the גמרא Gemara says באבוס של קרקע מי איכא
למאן דשרי? be'evus shel karka mi ika leman deshrei? No, that can't
be. Then how could anybody, even רבי דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, say it
would be allowed? הקא משוי גומות, haka mashvei gumot, he'll definitely come
to smooth out the ground. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר. Ela i
itmar hachi itmar. Rather if it was said, this is how it
was said. אמר רב חסדא מחלוקת באבוס של כלי. Amar Rav Chisda
machlokes be'evus shel kli. The debate is when it's a trough out
of some type of a vessel. אבל באבוס של קרקע דברי הכל
אסור. Aval be'evus shel karka divrei hakol asur. If it's on the
ground, everybody agrees it's forbidden. And now according to framing it this
way, the only issue the reason רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa would forbid
the other type of a trough is if you allow that, it'll
come to allowing it when it's straight on the ground. Okay, now
ונוטלין לפני בהמה, venotlin lifnei behema, you can take the grain that
or whatever the straw that one animal ate and put it in
front of another animal, even though it has his saliva and whatnot.
תנא
חדא, Tana chada, we taught one
ברייתא. braita. נוטלין מלפני בהמה שפיה יפה ונותנין לפני בהמה שפיה רע.
Notlin milifnei behema shepiha yafe venotnin lifnei behema shepiha ra. You can
take from one animal that has a nice mouth and put it
in front of another animal that has a nice mouth. bad mouth.
We'll see what this means. Okay. ותניא אידך, ve-tanya idach, and the
other ברייתא baraita says it in the reverse. נוטלין מלפני בהמה שפיה
רע ונותנין לפני בהמה שפיה יפה. notlin mi-lifne behemah she-piyah ra ve-notnin
lifne behemah she-piyah yafeh. You can take from an animal with a
bad mouth and put it in front of an animal with a
good mouth. So let's see what this means. אמר אביי, amar abaye,
אידי ואידי, idi ve-idi, מחמרא לקמי תורא שקלינן, mi-chamra le-kamei tura shaklinan,
everybody agrees that you can take from a donkey and put it
into front of a cow. מטורא לקמי חמרא לא שקלינן, mi-tura le-kamei
chamra lo shaklinan, but to take from a cow and put in
front of a donkey, that everybody agrees you can't do. Okay. And
these different ways of a nice mouth, bad mouth are different ways
of describing taking from a donkey and putting in front of a
cow. Let's take a look. והא דתניא נוטלין מלפני בהמה שפיה יפה
ve-ha de-tanya notlin mi-lifne behemah she-piyah yafeh בחמור, be-chamor, that's a donkey.
You can take from in front of a donkey. Now why is
it considered a nice mouth? דלא ריירי, de-la reyrei, it does not
have like a lot of spittle apparently as it's eating, or that
drools out of its mouth. ונותנין לפני בהמה שפיה רע ve-notnin lifne
behemah she-piyah ra בפרה, be-parah, that's by a cow. דאית ליה ריירי,
de-it leh reyrei, it has spittle. And that obviously explains why it's
only in that direction, because if a cow has a lot of
spittle that gets comes out of its mouth while it's eating, then
another animal wouldn't want to eat it. But apparently if a donkey
doesn't have that, so you can take donkey food that a donkey's
been eating and giving it to a cow. So now we understand
why it goes in that direction. What do you do with the
other way of framing it, of reversing the terms? והא דתניא נוטלין
מלפני בהמה שפיה רע ve-ha de-tanya notlin mi-lifne behemah she-piyah ra בחמור,
be-chamor, that way also means from a donkey. Why is here calling
a donkey a bad mouth? דלא דייק ואכיל, de-lo dayek ve-achil, because
it does not like it's not neat when it eats. It's like
or the other way around he says I'm sorry what it means
is that it's not it's not particular what it eats, right? It'll
eat all the like it'll eat thorns and thistles and whatnot. That's
what animals eat the thorns and thistles? It's donkeys says goats.
Who's which who's Eeyore in Winnie the Pooh? He's he's a donkey.
He's always eating the thorns and thistles, right? Okay
anyway okay that's how I know my farm animals through Winnie the
Pooh. ונותנין לפני בהמה שפיה יפה ve-notnin lifne behemah she-piyah yafeh בפרה
be-parah דדייק ואכיל, de-dayek ve-achil, it's more particular. Okay so but this
also so this maybe explains why you might have imagined it goes
in the opposite direction. Maybe if a donkey is less particular, maybe
you could go from a cow to a donkey because a donkey
is less particular. He says no, the the determining issue here is
the degree to which saliva gets mixed up and that's a concern
after a cow has eaten from it, it's not a concern after
a donkey has eaten from it. Yes, Charlie.
I'm surprised there's no mention of the fact that cows and goats
and sheep chew their cud and donkeys don't.
Why should that be? Oh because the chewing of the cud means
that the spit and so on?
Well yeah, it makes it'll make their mouth quite a bit different.
Yes. Is it an interesting question, does it do that as it's
actually eating or after it finishes getting all of the food into
it?
Then it brings it back up.
So right, so it wouldn't be as relevant to how it affected
the straw that it was eating. Okay. All right. Moving on to
the next משנה. mishnah. הקש שעל גבי המיטה, ha-kash she-al gabei ha-mitah,
so now that we're talking about straw, again it's an interesting collection
here, you know we are dealing much more with like just just
like all like like like a somewhat random, not really, but anyway
collection of very relevant הלכות halachot that apply around the house. We
were dealing a lot with food but then we moved into I
guess human food, animal's food and now since we mentioned straw we're
dealing with other things related to straw and whether it's מוקצה. muktzah.
So הקש שעל גבי המיטה, ha-kash she-al gabei ha-mitah, you have straw
that's on a bed. Now presumably the question here is at what
stage is that straw considered to be your mattress and at what
stage is it basically just normal straw which is מוקצה muktzah because
actually now it's funny because you could have thought that straw actually
קש kash is more like stubble. Right? I don't know what's the
difference between stubble and straw. But anyway רש"י Rashi says that סתם
stam how does it translate קש kash there? Stubble or straw? Straw.
Straw. Okay anyway so okay so תבן teven I think is straw
and קש kash is stubble. Stubble is I don't know if there's
whatever.
Stubble's the stuff that's left at the like you cut you cut
the wheat and or the corn and what's
left near the bottom is stubble.
It's the same thing.
Right. Okay either way. Anyway רש"י Rashi says although if it's animal
food it's not מוקצה muktzah and although if it's used for your
bed mattress it's not מוקצה, muktzah, רש"י Rashi says that in a
normal case we would assume that it's basically there for fuel. So
therefore it would be מוקצה. muktzah. So therefore it's on your bed.
What? Yeah somehow it happens to be on your bed. Now it
might be it might be that you put it on your bed
and intended to turn it into a mattress. But if you remember
from discussions before, if you take these natural parts of nature, these
parts of nature like sticks and stones and whatever, at what stage
does it need to stop being considered מוקצה muktzah and to be
considered like a vessel? To be considered so maybe just putting it
on your bed is not enough. So it's not exactly clear how
it got on your bed, although
the way רש"י Rashi describes it is that we're assuming that it's
still being designated for use of firewood and therefore מוקצה. muktzah. So
therefore what can you do if you want to now lie on
it? לא ינענענו בידו, lo yenanenu be-yado, you should not remove it
with your hand because it's מוקצה. muktzah. Move it with your hand.
אלא מנענעו ela menanenu Maybe and presumably you can
even move it, intentionally, you know, lie on it and move it
to get it off your bed, as long as you're not moving
it with your hand. And that's called טלטול גוף, tiltul guf, you
know, טלטול. tiltul. There are two terms by the way that the
גמרא's Gemara going to identify, but להלכה lehalacha we distinguish. One is
טלטול מן הצד, tiltul min hatzad, which is moving it with your
hand but moving it incidentally. Like I've got my, you know, here's
this מוקצה muktzeh thing in front of me and I've got my,
I don't know, my food back there, so to get to it
I go like that in order to get to my food. So
I've moved it, but I've moved it incidentally in the process of
getting to something else. But I haven't directly picked it up and
moved it aside. That's טלטול מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. This is
different, this is טלטול בגופו, tiltul begufo, which is actually not using
your hand, using other parts of your body, and just so you
know, although the גמרא Gemara we're about to read and רש"י Rashi
anticipating the גמרא Gemara identifies the two, להלכה lehalacha we distinguish it.
טלטול מן הצד tiltul min hatzad is allowed if you're doing it
for the purpose of a non מוקצה muktzeh item. So if I
want to get, you know, again, to like I want to get
to my ספר sefer back there, and I've got my wallet in
the way, I can go like this and you know, as I'm
reaching for my wallet, move it, you know, it moves as I'm
reaching for my ספר, sefer, it moves my wallet aside. That I
can do. But I cannot, you know, intentionally like, you know, sort
of like move that aside and then go for it, okay, because
that is, first of all, that's not incidental, okay, and I certainly
can't, you know, so that's like something that's, so that's what I
can't do טלטול מן הצד. tiltul min hatzad. טלטול מן הצד tiltul
min hatzad is only basically in the act of you know going
for דבר המותר. davar hamutar. טלטול בגופו tiltul begufo is different. טלטול
בגופו tiltul begufo not using my hands, but you know, using like
my elbows or something like that or pushing it like that, that
would be okay even if I was directly moving it, not indirectly
moving it. Okay, so that is a difference, although the גמרא Gemara
we're going to see is going to somewhat identify them. Let's so
that's the first case. אם היה מאכל בהמה, Im haya maachal beheima,
now if it was animal food, okay, then it's not מוקצה, muktzeh,
as we learned implicitly in the previous משנה, Mishna, או שהיה עליו
כר או סדין, o shehaya alav kar o sadin, or there was
a pillow or blanket on it, which now designates it as your
mattress, then מנענעו בידו, menaneho beyado, you can directly move it, it's
not מוקצה. muktzeh. מכבש של בעלי בתים, Machbash shel baale batim, if
you have a clothing press of that's you know like a home,
a home one, so you know, you basically
put your clothes in it, you've got some you know weight or
whatever, it you know, it like presses,
you know, presses down on it to remove the wrinkles, okay, so
you have that from your home, so מתירין אבל לא כובשין. matirin
aval lo kovshin. If the clothes are in it and have been
being pressed from before שבת, Shabbat, then now the way רש"י Rashi
sort of explains it is, like I don't know, imagine that this
is my, this is you know, this is my garment, I put
it on the base here, and then I put another big heavy
thing on top, and then I like put a peg in to,
you know, in some type of a frame that has holes in
it, and that peg keeps the heavy thing like secure in its
place. So מתירין matirin means that I can like remove the peg
and lift up the weight in order to get my clothes out.
That I can do. אבל לא כובשין, Aval lo kovshin, I cannot
actually press it on שבת Shabbat itself because that would be minimally,
a, it could be like a type of a תיקון, tikkun, you
could imagine of the כלי, kli, of the you know of the
garment, and number two, רש"י Rashi says it would also be for
after שבת. Shabbat. ושל כובסין, Veshel kovesin, however, it's a professional press,
one of laundrymen, לא יגע בו. lo yigga bo. Don't even touch
it. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says because why, so רש"י Rashi says
that it is, רש"י Rashi says the concern is that it's because
that you'll come to, that you'll come to like tighten the things
in it more. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, של כובסין לא
יגע בו, shel kovesin lo yigga bo, רש"י Rashi for the גמרא
Gemara רש"י Rashi says מפני שהוא עשוי לתקנו בגדים ותוחבו בחזקה
ומהדק והתרו שלא דומה לסתירתו. mipnei shehu asui letakno begadim vetochvo bechozka
umehadek vehataro shelo domeh lestirato. So רש"י Rashi says the problem is
is that because it's more professional, things are much tighter there and
it's more like you're you know you're building the you know you're
making something constructing something or undoing something, you know in terms of
the whole structure of the weight and of the press. That's the
way רש"י Rashi explains it. I mean you could have said there
are other issues, since we're talking about מוקצה, muktzeh, you could have
said sort of like maybe it's like a you know it's like
a מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, muktzeh machamat chisaron kis, it's a professional
type of a vessel. You could have made it a מוקצה muktzeh
issue. You could have made it an issue about תיקון tikkun of
the בגד, beged, although undoing wouldn't explain why you can't undo. But
anyway you could have made it a מוקצה muktzeh issue, רש"י Rashi
makes it more of an issue of like constructing and deconstructing. רבי
יהודה אומר אם היה מותר מערב שבת מתיר את כולו ומשמטו. Rabbi
Yehuda omer im haya muttar meerev Shabbat matir et kulo umshamtov. So
here מותר muttar does not mean permissible, it means from the word
what מותר muttar technically means, which is undone. Okay, so if it
was undone, right, you understand like אסור assur means bound, right? So
and להתיר lehatir means to undo, right? ברוך מתיר אסורים. Baruch matir
assurim. Okay, so you know so they say maybe some rabbis have
to make that you know anyway whatever. But
so here means that if it was, the way רש"י Rashi explains
it is... If the peg was already removed from before שבת Shabbat,
*Shabbat*, so it wasn't locked in the place but the weight was
still down on it, then you could remove the weight and get
out the garment even if it were from a, you know, from
a professional type of a press. Okay, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. *Rebbi Yehuda* says, so that's why it's understood here by רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* that even the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* the issue is
not מוקצה muktza *muktzah* but the issue is more the idea of
constructing and deconstructing. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav Nachman*, said רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*,
האי פוגלא *hai pugla*, so this we've had this before, a turnip,
okay, which is like a, like a triangle shape, מלמעלה למטה *milmala
lmata*, if it is from above to below, שרי Shari, *shari*, it's
permissible. Which what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* means is it means that if
it's in the, now it's not growing in the ground, you buried
it in dirt, but it's not, if it were growing it would
be a problem of קוצר *kotzer*, but you buried it in dirt.
If basically the top of it, the wide part is above and
the narrow is below, then you can pull it out of the
dirt, because then the dirt just falls around it and is moving
incidental. It's like a טלטול מן הצד tiltul min ha-tzad, *tiltul min
hatzad*, right? It's only incidentally being moved. שרי *shari*, that's permissible. מלמטה
למעלה *milmata lmala*, if however it's an inverted triangle and the wide
part is below, אסור assur, *assur*, that's forbidden, because as you're, you
know, pulling it out, when the wide part is coming, trying to
come out through a narrow hole, it's forcing the dirt away. And
you're holding on to it, so that's like יד *yad*, it's an
extension of your hand, it's a thing you're holding and the dirt
is being directly moved away. It's not just collapsing around it. Okay,
so it's a type of a, so so that is forbidden. אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה *Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava*, אמי בי רב
*ami bei Rav*, אמי בי רב *ami bei Rav*, תנינא דלא כרב
נחמן *tanina delo k'Rav Nachman*, our משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah* is not like
רב נחמן *Rav Nachman*. Because why? Our משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says הקש
שעל גבי המיטה לא ינענעו בידו אבל מנענעו בגופו *hakash sheal gabei
hamita lo yenaneu beyado aval menaneu begufo*, that the straw on the
bed you should not move it with your hand, but you can
move it with your body. ואם היה מאכל בהמה או שהיה עליו
כר או סדין מנענעו בידו *v'im haya maachal behemah o shehaya alav
kar o sadin menaneu beyado*, and which is not relevant for us,
if it was for animal food or if it was like a
mattress, then you can. שמע מינה Shema mina. *shma mina*, so you
see since you can move it with your body, טלטול מן הצד
tiltul min ha-tzad לא שמיה טלטול *tiltul min hatzad lo shmei tiltul*,
moving something incidentally is not moving. שמע מינה *shma mina*, you see.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here makes the equation that if you
can move it with your body, you can also move it here
like pulling up the turnip because you're basically focused on the turnip,
although it's true you are moving the dirt around it, but you're
moving the dirt around it in the process of removing the turnip
and that's considered to be incidental. So not פסיק רישא psik reisha?
*psik reisha* but it's defined as, yeah, but we're talking about מוקצה
muktza. *muktzah*. So it describes more the act of moving. It's not
like it's a different type of a moving. Incidental moving as opposed
to as opposed to, if I'm going, you can't say פסיק רישא
דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha dela nicha leh *psik reisha d'lo nicha
lei*, you can't apply those things. If I'm going for the turnip,
I know I've got to get the dirt, move the dirt out
of the way. If I'm going for my ספר *sefer*, I know
the only way I'm getting to it is by moving my wallet,
so it's like a ניחא ליה *nicha lei* and so on. But
the point is it's incidental. You're going for the דבר היתר *davar
heter* or you're moving the דבר היתר *davar heter* and incidentally the
other stuff is being moved. That's טלטול מן הצד *tiltul min hatzad*.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands from our משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* that
since טלטול בגוף *tiltul beguf* is מותר muttar *mutar*, טלטול מן הצד
*tiltul min hatzad* is מותר mutar, *mutar*. Okay, but there is but
you could make a distinction and I am saying that להלכה *l'halacha*
we do make a distinction. טלטול מן הצד *tiltul min hatzad* is
מותר *mutar* when you are handling the דבר המותר *davar hamutar* like
pulling the turnip out or going for it, going for my ספר
*sefer* and knocking the wallet away as I'm moving for it. And
טלטול בגוף *tiltul beguf* is מותר *mutar* even if you're directly focused
on the דבר האסור *davar ha'assur*. You've got your, whatever it is,
some type of a thing here in the middle of your, you
know, on the middle of your floor and it's I don't know,
you got your wallet in the middle of your floor or you've
got your Ming vase in the middle of your floor and you're
afraid that somebody's going to step on it and break it and
let's say that's, you know, that's case of a מוקצה muktza. מחמת
חסרון כיס kis *muktzah machmat chisron kis* or something. So you can
pick it up with your elbows, of course if your Ming vase
you gotta be very careful, but okay, whatever it is, you picked
your wallet up with your elbow or you kick your wallet under,
you know, under the couch, right? That's טלטול בגוף *tiltul beguf*. That's
a very different type of a thing than טלטול מן הצד *tiltul
min hatzad*. Now what you could say is that doesn't mean that
one is more מותר *mutar* than the other, it's just it's just
describing the phenomenon differently. טלטול מן הצד *tiltul min hatzad* is described
as dealing with a דבר מותר *davar mutar* and incidentally moving the
מוקצה muktzeh, *muktzah*. טלטול בגוף *tiltul beguf* is described, it's not like
one has a broader היתר *heter*, it's just what the act means.
One act means it's incidental to moving a דבר מותר *davar mutar*
and the other means it's moving with a different part of your
body. But okay, once they're different things, it's not clear why the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* can assume that you can learn one from the
other. Okay, so although this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* equates them, להלכה *l'halacha*
they are defined in those different ways. Okay, was there a question?
Yeah. When you pull up the turnip or whatever it is, at
that point you could you could pick it up and then eat
it because it was for food or is the object, but I
thought that would be under the category...
No, it's not it's not growing as I said, it's just buried,
so you it's not מוקצה muktzeh. *muktzah* and you can use it.
Oh like it's in a refrigerator or whatever it is...
Yeah, exactly, just to keep it cold or warm or whatever. Okay,
all right, so now we go on. Right, radish. Did I say
turnip before? It's a radish. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
moves on.
Where are we?
Okay. שמע מינה. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, הני פלפלי, hanei
pilpeli, so these peppers, מידק חדא חדא בקתא דסכינא, midek chada chada
bekata desakina, you can grind them one by one בקתא דסכינא bekata
desakina with the handle of a knife. What did we say before?
They had—did they have peppercorn or did they have peppercorn? They had
peppercorn. They didn't have our—the things we call pepper. Okay, anyway,
so these peppercorn—I mean, it sounds like that all the time, the
גמרא Gemara is talking about grinding it as a spice. So anyway,
these peppercorn you can grind them individually with the heel of the—of
a handle of a knife. שרי, it's permissible. תרתי אסירי, Tarti asiri,
but two at a time is forbidden.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, כיון דמשני, keivan demishani, once
you're doing a שינוי shinui because you're not grinding it with a
pepper mill, אפילו טובא נמי, afilu tuva nami, you can do a
lot of them. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, so רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says, מאן דסחי במיא—so man desachi bemaya anyway, let me
just end right there, okay? Which is now, that's pretty shocking because
basically it says that here you can do something which is a
מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbat? grinding spices, and as long as you
do a שינוי shinui it's allowed. Okay? So since when do we
allow you to do things with a שינוי shinui on שבת? Shabbat.
So there's a long תוספות Tosafot here that tries to figure out,
maybe we're talking about יום טוב, Yom Tov, not שבת. Shabbat. But
he says, no, no, no, if we're talking about יום טוב, Yom
Tov, we would have said it. And basically he brings up a
whole interesting discussion which we'll get to when we do ביצה, Beitzah,
that actually on יום טוב Yom Tov you'd be allowed to use
a peppercorn—a pepper mill, because spices that, you know, (a)
would lose their—some of their potency if you did it a day
before, and (b) there's a reason in the restaurants it's freshly ground
pepper. And (b), and (b),
you wouldn't necessarily have been able to anticipate you would have wanted,
so especially when you have both of those criteria together and according
to some maybe even only one of those, you could actually grind
it on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's אוכל נפש ochel nefesh and
so on. So this is clearly talking about שבת. Shabbat. And so
without actually פסקנינג paskening the הלכה halacha here, I will say that
there are times, ironically, sometimes we have so many different safeguards and
degrees removed and sometimes we allow a שינוי shinui of something that's
like really a מלאכה, melacha, like some types of ways about doing
like לש losh in, you know, if you're making like oatmeal or
something. Also we speak about like using the back of a spoon
to mix the water and the oatmeal and so on. Basically some
types of things are allowed with like a שינוי, shinui, maybe sometimes
require a double שינוי shinui and so on. But it is quite
shocking that once you're here grinding it—now the first position might have
required a double שינוי, shinui, both one at a time and with
the heel of a thing, but רבא Rava says you can even
do a lot.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, so says
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, סחי sachi is with the implement used for—no,
מדאורייתא, mide'oraita, yeah.
Right, this is a שינוי, shinui, right. So אמר רב יהודה, Amar
Rav Yehuda, מאן דסחי במיא, man desachi bemaya, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says
somebody that goes and—and sort of bathes in water, okay? You know,
you can't—there are limits about like where you go swimming, you know,
that—not to swim in a river, you might come to make a
raft. On the other hand, you can go in a bathtub or
bathhouse if it's not water—if it's not heated water and so on.
So anyway, so if you're swimming in water in a permissible context,
לינגיב נפשיה ברישא, lingiv nafshei berisha, first dry yourself, והדר ליסלק, vehadar
lislok, and then you can get up out of where you're—you know,
out of the bath. Obviously you can't dry yourself too well when
you're still—maybe you stand up in the bath or something or dry
yourself immediately as you get out, but dry yourself right away. Why?
דילמא אתי לאתויי ארבע אמות בכרמלית, dilma ati le'atuyei arba amot bekarmelit,
because if you don't, you'll come to carry the water on your
body as you're walking outside and you'll come to carry in a
כרמלית. karmelit.
So now by the way, this issue, even if it's a כרמלית
karmelit and not a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, even if it's only
דרבנן, derabbanan, we have to make the safeguard. By the way, this
is why
אשכנזים—ספרדים go swimming on שבת. Shabbat. You know, again, there's questions about
heated water because there's a גזירה gezeirah you'll come even if it
was heated from beforehand, you'll come to heat it on שבת. Shabbat.
But if it's not heated water and it's in a swimming pool,
there's nothing in the גמרא Gemara that says you can't do it.
אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't, it's a מנהג minhag that goes back about how
long, about 1600 years, maybe more, 1700 years. And the reason is
is because of all the concerns, incidental concerns that are around swimming.
Number one is you'll carry the water on you. Number two is
you'll come to squeeze out the
towel—סחיטה. schita. Number three is you'll come to squeeze out your hair.
So because of all those various concerns, that's why for
אשכנזים, Ashkenazim a מנהג minhag developed. Again, I'm trying to remember when
it started,
14th century, maybe earlier. Anyway, that we do not fully immerse ourselves
even in cold water on שבת. Shabbos Yes.
But you don't care about the water, you prefer not to carry
the water, you're not going to do anything with it. And you
don't care about the water you're squeezing out either.
Well, okay, the fact that you don't care about the water you're
squeezing out, that depends what the problem of
סחיטה schita
is. But the other part of סחיטה schita is not just that
you want the liquid you're getting, but you're cleaning the thing that
you are squeezing water out of, although, you know,
the ליבון libbun aspect. Look, it's true, these are basically—you're right, it's
a good point that even ignoring the fact that it's a כרמלית
karmelit or whatnot, a lot of this is a type
of
a
פסיק רישא psik reisha, דלא ניחא ליה where basically indirect...
Right, and there is cases where you are allowed to walk through
water and there is long תוספותים *Tosfosim* that discuss when we're concerned
you'll come to squeeze out your clothes and when you're not.
Okay, like going to the מקוה *Mikvah*.
Right. Okay, so מקוה *Mikvah* is different. מקוה *Mikvah* was always accepted.
מקוה *Mikvah* is such an exception that we even allow heat in
מקוואות *Mikvahs*, even though according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know,
heated water is clearly אסור *asur* to go into on שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat*.
But weren't they worried about being מעביר *maavir* water and you don't
want on you and you don't want to be squeezing out your
towel, why would מקוה *Mikvah* be different?
Because they always excluded מקוה *Mikvah* because women have to go to
the, you know, מקוה *Mikvah* on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*.
Yeah, but men.
Oh, men. Yeah, once it was excluded, it's true, מקוה *Mikvah* somehow
was always, always got a pass on that. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues says like this.
I mean for men too have that מנהג *minhag*, you know, anyway,
if they don't go, you know, some that's based on the idea
that they can't דאווען *daven* or other types of things, anyway, it
doesn't matter, what could I tell you, no, מנהג מקוה *minhag Mikvah*
was always excluded from that. אמר רב יהודה *Amar Rav Yehuda*, מן
*man*, okay, we just did that. אי הכי *ee hachi* says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, כי קא נחית נמי קא דחי כוחו ארבע אמות
*ki ka nachis nami ka dachi kocho arba amos* ואסור *v'asur*, when
you go into the water through your energy, the water will be
pushed ארבע אמות *arba amos* like when you had maybe like dive
in or something, the water gets displaced around you ארבע אמות *arba
amos* and the the you know space itself is a כרמלית *carmelis*
so you're moving that water ארבע אמות *arba amos* in the כרמלית
*carmelis*. So says גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ואסור *v'asur* should be forbidden, so
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, כוחו בכרמלית לא גזרו *kocho b'carmelis lo
gozru*. Because you know you're that's not directly doing it, that's just
your כח *koach*, you know, because the sort of waves created by
your body, the energy, you know by your body, and that they
did not make a גזירה *gezera* around. Okay, of course the way
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* phrased it it sounds like it's not such
a גזירה *gezera* like it'll definitely happen, but anyways that they weren't
concerned about. אמר אביי Abaye ואיתימא רב יהודה *Amar Abaye v'isema Rav
Yehuda*. Now אביי Abaye, *Abaye* says and some say רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* says, it's not exactly clear what all these statements are doing
together, although these are רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* statements, seems to be
the things that are linking them. The רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* was
on the pepper and the רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* was on the
bathing. And now אביי Abaye *Abaye* and some say רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* says, טינא דעל גבי רגלו מקנחו בקרקע ואין מקנחו בכותל *tina
d'al gabi raglo mikancho b'karka v'ain mikancho b'kosel*. If you have if
you have like plaster on your legs that you got your legs
like you know muddy or got plaster on it and you have
to scrape it off, so you can scrape it off on the
קרקע *karka* but not on the כותל *kosel*. So אמר רבא Rava
*amar Rava* מאי טעמא בכותל לא *mai ta'ama b'kosel lo*, why do
you not want to scrape it on the wall? משום דמיחזי כבונה
*mishum d'mechze k'boneh* because you're winding up adding plaster to the wall
or you're adding something on the wall and it's like you're building.
So it says, הבנין הך לאו *habinyan hach lo*? That's like the
building of like of like you know
field hands. I don't exactly know what that's supposed to mean. I
guess so, it means it's amateur, yeah, it's not a real it's
it's not real building is clearly the intent.
What about just the opposite because if you're in the קרקע *karka*.
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say. אלא
אמר רבא Rava מקנחו בכותל *Ella amar Rava mikancho b'kosel* better do
it on the wall because you know whatever ואין מקנחו בקרקע *v'ain
mikancho b'karka* not on the ground, דילמא אתי לאשוויי גומות *dilma osi
l'ashvoye gumos*, you'll come to smooth out the ground and that'll be
like a type of a בונה *boneh* or חורש *choresh* or whatever.
איתמר *Itmar* it was said, מר בריה דרבינא אמר אחד זה ואחד
זה אסור *Mar brei d'Ravina amar echad ze v'echad ze asur*, either
way it's forbidden. רב פפא אמר אחד זה ואחד זה מותר *Rav
Papa amar echad ze v'echad ze mutar*, either way it's permissible. למר
בריה דרבינא *l'Mar brei d'Ravina* one that says either way it's forbidden,
במאי מקנח *b'mai mikanchei* how do you מקנח *mikanchei* how do you
get the plaster off of your leg? לי, מקנח ליה בקורה *Le,
mikanchei lei b'kora*, you find some type of a קורה *kora* that's
on the ground so it's neither wiping it on the ground you
know which is a type of a smoothing the ground and or
wiping it on wall which adds to a structure, you're wiping it
on some type of a קורה *kora*. Or go swimming, right. So
אמר רבא Rava *amar Rava* for us the question would be what
happens if you get dog poop on your shoes, where do you
wipe it off of you know, so there you wipe it off
on the grass, that actually could be a type of a זורע
*zoreia*. Yeah, because they're adding you know it's what, not with
dog. Really dog excrement doesn't have the same types of fertilizer? Really?
That's not good fertilizer? Interesting.
It would still be ממרח *mimarei*.
ממרח *mimarei*, yeah I don't know if it's ממרח *mimarei*, you're not
trying to smooth you're just trying to get it off or the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* doesn't here seem to be concerned about ממרח *mimarei*.
You could be pulling
out, pulling out the grass. Yeah a lot of these things are
certainly you know like like like not פסיק רישא *psik reisha*, לא
ניחא ליה lo nicha lei, *lo nicha lay*, but anyway, right. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואמר רבא ve'amar Rava, *v'amar
Rava* לא ליפתופ איניש כובא *lo lispod inish kubba*. So now apparently
we made the move from רב *Rav* through רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*
to רבא Rava. *Rava*, did I skip? אמר רבא Rava, לא ליתיב
איניש אפומא דלחיא *Amar Rava lo laseiv inish appuma d'leichaya*. Anyway we
somehow skip because through the רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* making רבא Rava
*Rava*, it's a lot of don't do this don't do this don't
do that like common שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* scenarios. Don't sit by the
mouth of the of the of the post, meaning that you have
a מבוי *mavoi* right which is like you know a court alleyway
that various courtyards open up into and effectively based on the houses
and in the courtyards it's considered surrounded by walls, but you can
only carry in it if it has a לחי *lechi* by the
third side which is the open end. And one of the functions
of the לחי *lechi* is to signal... you that you are about
to be
leaving the alleyway that's surrounded by walls and you're about to be
going out into the public domain, so don't carry from one to
the other. So it's there as a היכר. Okay, so so רבא
Rava over there says don't sit right up against that post because
you'll be sitting there and you're not looking at the post, your
body is actually, the post is behind you, your body is against
it, and therefore what's going to happen?
Where are we? דילמא מגנדרא ליה חפץ, dilma megandara lei chefetz,
maybe an object will roll away from you and out of the
alleyway into the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim ואתי לאתויי va'ati la'atuyei and
then you'll go and you'll grab it and you'll bring it back
and you'll forget that you're leaving the alleyway into רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim because you're right there sitting at, you're covering up essentially the
marker. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says, ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava,
and רבא Rava said, לא לצדד אינש כובא, lo litzaded inishi kuva,
a person should
not like sort of adjust a barrel, like you've got this big
barrel of wine and like you move it and you fix to
a place and you settle it in its place. דילמא אתי לאשווי
גומות dilma ati lashavei gumos because you know it's big and it's
heavy and you're moving it against the ground and maybe you'll come
to smooth out the ground in the process. ואמר רבא, רבא says,
לא להדיק אינש אודרא בפומא דשישא, lo lehadik inish udra bepuma deshisha,
a person should not tighten a cloth by the opening
of a pitcher. דילמא
אתי לידי סחיטה dilma ati lidei sechita because maybe it'll come to
squeeze it because now it's whatever it's oil in there and you're
tightening it, so it's absorbing the oil and in the process of
tightening it the oil will be squeezed out.
And is this the kind of oil you're going to want or
is this...
again, that's a whole discussion the ראשונים Rishonim have. Is it only
a problem when you want the things you're squeezing out? But certainly
if it gets squeezed out and goes back into the vessel, then
then you want it. אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, טיט על
גבי בגדו, tit al gabei begado, now that we're talking about plaster
and mud and stuff, if you've got plaster on your garment,
מחסככו מבפנים ואין מחסככו מבחוץ. mechaschecho mibifnim ve'ein mechaschecho mibachutz. You can
rub it away from the inside, not the outside. So I presume
what that means is if like if I've got it here on
the like on my lapel, doing it on the outside is like
doing this to get it out. Doing it from the inside is
like doing it like that, right, you know like from behind it,
not on top, so it's much less sort of noticeable. Okay, now
by the way, so if the idea of laundering is if something
gets embedded into a cloth, if it's on the surface, certainly if
there's no cloth around like I get stuff on my shoes or
on the table, that's not laundering. It's totally on the surface. Even
on the surface of a cloth, if it's not embedded in the
cloth and you're just scraping off the stuff that's on the surface,
that's okay. The problem is at what stage do you stop getting
off the stuff that's on the surface and start getting off the
stuff that's embedded into the cloth itself? So anyway, he says don't
do it from the outside, do it from the inside. מיתיבי, meisvei,
I'll ask you on this. So it says... so anyway it's not
clear if the difference is that one case it's like one case
you know that in both cases technically it's מותר but it's more
like עובדא דחול uvda dechol and it's more, you know,
looks
problematic when you
do it
the other way, or is it
when you
do it from
the inside it's a שינוי? shinui? When you do it from the
inside רש״י Rashi says it's not as it, you know, doesn't look
as bad, so it's, you know, maybe it's not as effective, it's
not, you know, in terms of getting stuff that's embedded. Not exactly
clear what the level of difference is, but these are concerns around
the around laundering. If you look at רש״י Rashi though two lines
on the bottom an important רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says ומלבן ממש
לא הוי, umelabben mamash lo havei, רש״י Rashi says whatever you do
this isn't real laundering דאיכא דאין שם מים, de'eika de'ein sham mayim,
you don't have water. So according to רש״י, Rashi, you cannot transgress
biblical laundering even if you are getting it out from being embedded
in the cloth without the use of water, which is interesting, a
lot of ראשונים Rishonim and פוסקים Poskim disagree. Anyway, so now the
גמרא Gemara, says מיתיבי, meisvei, I'll ask you on this. טיט על
גבי מנעלו, tit al gabei min'alo, if you have plaster on your
shoe where there's no problem of laundering because it's a smooth surface,
מגררו בגב סכין, megarero begav sakkin, excuse me, that's two words, with
the back of a knife. ושל בגדו, vesheal begado, and from the
and from your if it's on your garment, מגררו בציפורן, megarero betzipporen,
you can scrape it with your fingernail, ובלבד שלא יחסכך, uvilvad shelo
yechasches, as long as you don't like rub the garment together. מאי
לאו שלא יחסכך כלל, mai lav shelo yechasches klal, doesn't it mean
you can't rub it at all? Even from the
inside? לא שלא יחסכך מבחוץ אלא מבפנים. lo shelo yechasches mibachutz ela
mibifnim. All right, as long as you do it from the inside,
not a classic way of rubbing the garment, that's okay.
Okay, I guess fingernails is less classic than rubbing.
Yeah, certainly looks less like you're you know when you're doing this,
this is that's what you do when you launder things, like you
put a treat the stain and you rub it together. And fingernails
anyway also usually just gets off the surface stuff. Okay. אמר רב
איביא אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rav Ivya amar Rav
Elazar amar Rav Yanai, מגרדין מנעל חדשה ולא ישנה. megarin mina chadasha
velo yeshana. You can scrape, you know, mud off of a new
shoe but not an old one because רש״י Rashi says an old
one you actually the leather maybe isn't
as
good... It would smooth out maybe the leather from various bumps or
whatnot. So the גמרא Gemara says במה מגררו, Beme megarero, what do
you use to scrape it? So אמר רב אבהו Amar Rav Abbahu
בגב סכין, Be-gav sakkin, what we said before, the back of a
knife. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so apparently not the edge of a
knife because that really will cut things, but the back of a
knife is like narrow and thin, so it'll be good for scraping,
but it won't actually, like, dig deep in or cut things away.
Okay. אמר ליה ההוא סבא Amar lei hahu saba סמי דידך מקמי
הא Sami didach mikamei ha דתני רבי חייא, Detani Rebbe Chiya, remove
your teaching from the following teaching of רבי חייא, Rebbe Chiya, which
is what? אין מגרין לא מן החדש ולא מן הישן, Ein megarin
lo min hachadash velo min hayashan, you cannot scrape neither a new
one or an old one. ולא יסוך את רגלו שמן והוא בתוך
המנעל או בתוך הסנדל, Velo yasuch et raglo shemen vehu betoch hamin'al
o betoch hasandal, and you also, another point about relating to feet
and shoes, you cannot put oil on your leg when your leg
is in the shoe או בתוך הסנדל o betoch hasandal or in
the sandal, because then the oil will trickle down into your onto
your shoe and the leather and you'll be treating your leather. Exactly.
Okay. ולא יסוך את רגלו שמן והוא בתוך
המנעל או בתוך הסנדל, Velo yasuch et raglo shemen vehu betoch hamin'al
o betoch hasandal, אבל סך את רגלו שמן ומניח בתוך המנעל או
בתוך הסנדל, Aval sach et raglo shemen umaniach betoch hamin'al o betoch
hasandal, you can first put oil on your leg, you know, because
again they would rub themselves with oil, and then you don't have
to dry it off before you put it on your shoe, then
it's not like treating your shoe, then it's completely incidental. וסך כל
גופו שמן, Vesach kol gufo shemen, and similarly you can put oil
on your whole body ומתגלגל על גבי קטבליא Umitgalgel al gabei katavliya
and you can then sort of lie and roll around on a
type of like a leather mat. Now again, presumably this means that
it's not like you're trying to get the oil on it, that's
incidental, but you don't have to worry if it happens incidentally. What,
can you then slide yourself
off on this leather mat?
Presumably if you're doing it not for that purpose of treating the
leather. Okay. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, so says רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, with all these things the question is and if you
did it, is it biblical, is it rabbinic? And if it's biblical,
why isn't it a problem? Is it פסיק רישא? פסיק רישא דניחא
ליה, psik reisha denicha lei, לא ניחא ליה, you know, that's sort
of not being discussed exactly how to unpack these issues. But the
point being that, you know,
somehow it's okay, makes more sense if the whole concern is rabbinic
to begin with. אמר רב חסדא לא שנו אלא לצחצחו אבל לעבדו
אסור, Amar Rav Chisda lo shanu ela letzach-tzecho aval le'avdo assur, this
whole issue is if you're only coming to like to brighten it,
meaning, you know, by adding the oil it's like giving yourself like
a shoe shine, you're coming to shine it. But if you're coming
to actually treat the leather, it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says
לעבדו פשיטא, le'avdo peshita, of course you can't treat leather with the
oil. ואטו, Ve-atu, and in addition, וצחצחו, vetzach-tzecho, you said to make
it shining, it sounds like you're intending to do this. He maybe
read the ברייתא braita that you can roll around, you know, with
the intent to get it on the leather or
put your leg in the shoe with the intent to get the
oil onto the onto the shoe if you're doing it to shine
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, really, you can intentionally do it?
וצחצחו מי איכא דשרי, Vetzach-tzecho mi ika desharei, who would permit
intentionally adding oil to leather even if it's just to shine it?
אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר, Ela i itmar hachi itmar, rather if
it was taught here's how it was taught. אמר רב חסדא לא
שנו אלא שיעור לצחצחו, Amar Rav Chisda lo shanu ela shiur letzach-tzecho,
when do we allow you to lie on the leather mat or
to put your leg in the shoe? If the amount of oil
you have on is only enough to give the leather a shine.
Then even if you did it incidentally, like I said, maybe it's
not a פסיק רישא, maybe it's anyway not a דאורייתא de-oraita if
you only shine the leather without really treating the leather. אבל שיעור
לעבדו, Aval shiur le'avdo, but if there's enough oil on your leg
or on the body that it's enough to actually cause the leather
to be treated,
מעבד, me'abed, you know, treating leather is one of the אבות מלאכות,
avos melachos, אסור, then forbidden, then you can't even do it even
if it's incidental. Okay, so that works now better to understand that
the whole concern is when you're at a rabbinic level of concern
then it's okay, but once it's the amount that even if it's
not intentional, once it's biblical, that's obviously could be a biblical issue,
that's a different story.
But כל גופו, kol gufo, I mean wouldn't you have enough?
Yes, but you're also lying on a big flat mat, so how
much gets on any one place? תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan לא יצא
קטן במנעל גדול אבל יוצא הוא בחלוק גדול. lo yeitzei katan bemin'al
gadol aval yotzei hu bechaluk gadol. A
now קטן katan here does not mean a minor, at least the
way רש"י Rashi sees it, it means a small person can't go
out with the shoe of a big person because then you will
come to take it off and carry in רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
אבל יוצא הוא בחלוק גדול, Aval yotzei hu bechaluk gadol, you can
go out with a oversized clothes because you're not about to strip
in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. ולא תצא אשה במנעל מרופט, Velo
teitzei isha bemin'al merufat, and a woman should not go out
with a shoe that is מרופט, merufat, which has like torn above,
because women will be more sensitive to wearing clothes that don't look
great and therefore she'll come to take it off and carry it
in רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. And
what's the line? Okay, whatever I won't say it. Anyway there's some
line what is it? A man will wear something that's comfortable no
matter... No matter what it looks like and a woman will wear
something that looks good no matter how uncomfortable. Okay. Okay. ולא תצא
אשה במנעל מרופת v'lo teitzei isha b'minal marufas ולא תחלוץ בו v'lo
tachloz bo and she also cannot use it for חליצה chalitza because
it's not a whole shoe. ואם חלצה v'im chaltza and if she
does and if it was used for חליצה, chalitza, חליצה כשרה, chalitza
ksheira, then the חליצה chalitza is valid because בדיעבד b'di'eved it does
count as a shoe. ואין יוצאים במנעל חדש v'ein yotzim b'minal chadash
and you don't go out with a new shoe. Okay. Now, באיזה
מנעל אמרו, b'eizeh minal amru, what type of new shoe did they
say? במנעל של אשה, b'minal shel isha, with a woman's shoe. Now
what's the problem with a new one? So רש"י Rashi says the
problem is that if it's not like if it's new, it hasn't
been broken in, it doesn't fit exactly. So again the woman will
be more concerned with, you know, with the exact question of appearances.
So if it's brand new she might come to take it off,
decide she doesn't like how it looks or how it fits more
than a man. תני בר קפרא, Tani Bar Kappara, so בר קפרא
Bar Kappara taught: לא שנו אלא שלא יצא בו שעה אחת מבעוד
יום. lo shanu ela shelo yatza bo sha'ah achas mibode yom. New
means it hasn't been worn even like once. אבל יצא בו מערב
שבת, aval yatza bo me'erev Shabbos, if it was worn if she
walked with it around with it outside on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
מותר, then it's permissible.
What?
over here it says that the they quote רש"י Rashi saying that
the concern for the woman is comfort, not appearance.
רש"י doesn't say, he says אם אינה מכוון למידת רגלה. im einena
mechyuvan l'midos ragla. If it doesn't fit the shape of her foot.
So I'm not sure that's the case today. Right. I'm not sure
if that means that it's about comfort. רש"י just says it doesn't
fit, which is interesting because again the גמרא Gemara said that by
a man if it was really it was a large shoe, it
was clearly it didn't fit, we wouldn't be concerned that the man
would take it off. So here the point is more like it's
like more of a minor like non-fitting. Exactly. Right. Okay. תא שמע?
ta shema? Okay so, אבל יצא מערב שבת מותר. aval yatza me'erev
Shabbos mutar. תני חדא, Tani chada, now finishing up the issue of
shoes, שומטין מנעל מעל גבי אימוס, shomtin minal me'al gabei imos, you
can remove a shoe from the from the what's it called? Not
the mold. What what do you put on when you're making it?
Like a horn or something? A last. L-A-S-T. Yeah. Okay. That would
be the technical term. Okay so you cannot remove it from the
last, from like the you know from the horn that it's on.
I mean you can, excuse me. ותני אידך, v'tani idach, we taught
another ברייתא: Baraisa: אין שומטין, ein shomtin, you can't remove it. This
is as it's finishing in the very last stages of its construction.
Right? So now finally it's been finished before שבת Shabbat. but it
wasn't removed from that mold and now you want to remove it.
So what's the problem? So לא קשיא. lo kashya. So first let's
explain the contradiction. הא רבי אליעזר הא רבנן. ha Rabbi Eliezer ha
Rabbanan. It's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Now we taught in a משנה: Mishnah מנעל שעל גבי אימוס
רבי אליעזר מטהר. minal she'al gabei imos Rabbi Eliezer metaher. So this
is from not שבת but from כלים. keilim. If it's on this
form, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's טהור tahor because it is
not yet a vessel. וחכמים מטמאין, v'chachamim metamin, the חכמים Chachamim say
it's טמא. tamei. So it's totally finished but it hasn't been removed.
At what stage what is called a shoe? Like you now actually
you do understand the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Even if
technically it's all finished, while it's still on that like form that
it was being constructed on, it doesn't yet maybe have that identity
of a shoe until it's removed. You don't get that? I totally
get that. At least, you know, just sort of societally about how
we identify that thing. Okay. וחכמים v'chachamim say no, once it's done
it's done. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's מוקצה muktzeh
because it's not yet a shoe. And according to the חכמים Chachamim
it's a shoe and it's not מוקצה. muktzeh. So the גמרא says:
הניחא לרבא. hani l'Rava. That's good according to רבא. דאמר דבר שמלאכתו
לאיסור בין לצורך גופו בין לצורך
מקומו מותר שפיר. d'amar davar shemlachto l'issur bein l'tzorech gufo bein l'tzorech
mekomo mutar shapir. According to רבא, now says okay we get the
shoe difference whether the shoe is מוקצה. muktzeh But how can you
move the actual, you know,
אימוס? imos? How can you actually move the last? because what we're
assuming that the way you get it off is like you sort
of pull them apart. Okay. Because isn't that a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור,
kli shemlachto l'issur, something used for professionally and used for making shoes?
So it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemlachto l'issur. So you're and
you know it's true you're you're using it לצורך. l'tzorech. But fine
that's good according to רבא that says a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli
shemlachto l'issur you can move לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו. l'tzorech gufo v'l'tzorech
mekomo. We get why you can remove the shoe if it's according
to the חכמים Chachamim once it's considered a shoe and you can
move the last, it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemlachto l'issur but
it's being moved לצורך. l'tzorech.
אלא אביי, ella Abaye, but according to אביי דאמר לצורך גופו מותר
לצורך מקומו אסור, d'amar l'tzorech gufo mutar l'tzorech mekomo assur, you can
move it לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo not לצורך מקומו, l'tzorech mekomo, מה
איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? What can you say? Now here's a
fascinating thing. If I were to ask you if you're trying to
remove this, you know, whatever last or whatever we call it from
this shoe and you're pulling it out so now you can use
the shoe, is that considered לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo or לצורך מקומו?
l'tzorech mekomo? What would you have said? It's
neither.
What?
we're talking about the last, not the shoe.
Right. Moving of the last. Are you moving the last? Are you
moving it לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo or לצורך מקומו? l'tzorech mekomo? So
the גמרא says מקומו, mekomo, it's in the way. It's in the
way of you getting your foot into the shoe. But somehow I
would have said you know you're I don't know somehow initially it
struck me as more of a לצורך גופו. l'tzorech gufo. I know
לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo is like you take the hammer and you
bang with it and here you're not doing anything with it, but
somehow it's
like you're using
it. Okay, so anyway the גמרא understands that it's צורך מקומו. tzorech
mekomo. So according to אביי, you can't move a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemilachto le-issur for צורך מקומו. tzorech mekomo. How can you—I get
the shoe isn't מוקצה, muktzeh but how do you remove the last?
So the גמרא says, מאי למימרא? mai le-meimra? So the גמרא says,
הכא במאי עסקינן, hakha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? The
רפוי, rafui, that it is not tightly on, it's loosely on, so
you can get the shoe off just by moving the shoe without
having to move the last. Okay, דתניא, d'tanya, רבי יהודה אומר אם
היה רפוי מותר. Rabbi Yehuda omer im haya rafui muttar. If it
was רפוי, rafui, it's permissible because then you don't have to move
the last. So now the גמרא says, okay, now let's focus on
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda טעמא דרפוי, ta'ama d'rafui, so we get רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? says that it has to be loose. הא לאו
רפוי לא, ha lav rafui lo, but if it's tight, no. הניחא
לאביי, hani kha l'Abaye, I get according to אביי why it makes
a difference if it's tight or loose. דאמר דבר שמלאכתו לאיסור לצורך
גופו מותר לצורך מקומו אסור. d'amar davar shemilachto le-issur letzorech gufo muttar
letzorech mekomo assur. שפיר, shappir, so I get why if it's tight
you can't move it, because then it would entail
removing the last and you can't do
it, it's מלאכתו לאיסור לצורך מקומו. milachto le-issur letzorech mekomo. אלא לרבא,
ella l'Rava, how does רבא explain רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda דאמר בין
לצורך גופו בין לצורך מקומו מותר. d'amar bein letzorech gufo bein letzorech
mekomo muttar. רבא says that even for צורך מקומו tzorech mekomo you
can move it. So according—why would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda distinguish between
whether the shoe is on tight or the shoe is on loose?
מאי איריא רפוי, mai irya rafui, why loose? אפילו לא רפוי נמי,
afillu lo rafui nami, even if it's not loose, even if it's
tight, it shouldn't be a problem. So the גמרא says, היא דרבי
יהודה משום דרבי אליעזר היא. hee d'Rabbi Yehuda mishum d'Rabbi Eliezer hee.
No, that of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not his own position,
it's the concern is with the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
who says that it is not yet a shoe.
דתניא רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר אם היה רפוי מותר. d'tanya
Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer im haya rafui muttar. Meaning, רבי
יהודה isn't talking about the last. The reason he says that loose
works is that the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says when the
shoe is still on the last it's not yet a shoe, what
happens if you haven't removed it but you've loosened it? It's not
tight on it the way it would be as you're still working
on it, it's all been loosened, it just hasn't been slipped off.
So at that stage, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer will say it will
be a shoe. So according to him, the reason of loose is
that then it allows you even according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
to move the shoe, that's what makes it a shoe. הדרן עלך
כל כתבי, hadran lach kol kitvei, that's the end of that perek
which, as we saw, started with food but got into a wide
range of things. Let's start now the next perek which gets us
back into—we can never get away from מוקצה. muktzeh So we touched
on מוקצה muktzeh before, we continue with מוקצה. muktzeh. נוטל אדם את
בנו ואבן בידו, notel adam et b'no v'even b'yado,
you can pick up your kid even though your kid is holding
onto a stone. So you're incidentally moving the stone, but it doesn't
matter because this is
presumably even without טלטול מן הצד, because fundamentally you're moving your kid,
right? So that's basically the act of what you're doing. If you
want, you could also call it the טלטול מן הצד point, but
it seems like it's even more than that, that
fundamentally you're moving your kid.
You don't even have to tell them to try to drop a
stone?
Right. I mean we're assuming not the age of חינוך chinuch whatever.
וכלכלה, v'khalkala, you can move also a basket ואבן בתוכה v'even betokhah
that has a stone in it, presumably other things as well, but
it also happens to have a stone in it, but the stone
is completely incidental to what you are doing. ומטלטלין תרומה טמאה עם
הטהורה, u-metaltelin terumah t'meiah im ha-tehorah,
similarly if you have תרומה טמאה terumah t'meiah which is מוקצה muktzeh,
because what can you do with it on שבת, mixed up with
תרומה טהורה, terumah t'horah, you can in a bundle you can move
them all. ועם החולין v'im ha-chullin or with חולין. chullin. Again, somehow
in which part of what you're moving is not מוקצה muktzah. and
presumably the reason you're moving it is for the non-מוקצה muktzah, item,
the fact that the other stuff is bundled up together does not
have to be your concern. So all these are three scenarios of
very much the same type of case. רבי יהודה אומר אף מעלין
את המדומע באחד ומאה. Rabbi Yehuda omer af malin et ha-meduma b'echad
u-meiah. Now this is, while we're talking about תרומה, terumah, completely unrelated
to the מוקצה muktzeh, discussion. He says that if you have a
mixture of תרומה terumah and חולין chullin on שבת, so the way
that you can sort of if it's
a hundred to one proportions then it's בטל, battel, but you have
to remove one of the
units מעלין. malin. So he says you're allowed to do that on
שבת. So the question is, since we're talking about תרומה, terumah, the
question's like why? It would seem that it's a type of way
of like fixing the food. You're not allowed to take תרומה, terumah,
but this is a mixture where it's already been taken and now
it's mixed up. So we'll see about that later in the גמרא.
Let's take a look now as we first focus on מוקצה. muktzeh,
אמר רבה, amar Raba, said רבה, Raba, הוציא תינוק חי וכיס תלוי
בצוארו חייב משום כיס. hotzi tinok chai v'kis tali b'tzavaro chayav mishum
kis. Okay, so now we've been talking about מוקצה, muktzeh but the
גמרא is going to turn our attention to carrying and a similar
question: what are you carrying when there are two things? So if
you take a live infant with like a
money pouch around its
neck and you take it outside in רשות הרבים, r'shus ha-rabim, you're
חייב chayav for carrying the money pouch, not the infant—חי נושא את
עצמו—but chai nosei et atzmo yes the money pouch. And the fact
that it's attached to the infant doesn't redefine it that you're not
carrying it. No, I'm sorry, you're also carrying the money pouch and
that you're חייב chayav for.
What was the משנה case then?
We'll see, there's a reason we're quoting this. תינוק מת וכיס תלוי
לו בצוארו, tinok meit v'kis tali lo b'tzavaro, however, if the infant
is dead... is dead, God forbid, and he's got the money pouch,
פטור. patur. You're exempt. Now, why are you exempt on either? So
you're exempt on the dead baby because of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה
melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufo is
which basically is that presumably there you're removing it not because you
want it somewhere else, but just because like you don't want it
here.
That's one way of explaining why taking a dead body out is
considered מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufo. How about though
the money pouch? So why is that so, you know, different? So
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot have different explanations. It either could be
the money pouch also is מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eino tzricha
l'gufo. It's not like you're trying to bring the money pouch somewhere.
Again, you're just trying to get the body out of the house
with everything that's on it. Or, you know, רש״י Rashi says maybe
you would there the money
by the first case, the money pouch is a little independent of
the kid. You're going to want your money pouch back. Here the
money pouch is sort of with the kid, maybe God, bury him
with it. You know, somehow by being on the child, it stirs
up your emotions, makes you remember how he was playing with it.
So somehow here it's more seen as something that's connected to the
child, this dead infant, rather than in the first case. Okay, so
that's interesting that distinction, but we're going to focus on the first
case. So let's take a look. תינוק
חי וכיס תלוי לו בצווארו חייב משום כיס. tinok chai v'kis taluy
lo b'tzavaro chayav mishum kis. So when you take out the infant,
you're חייב chayav for the money pouch. Says the גמרא, וליחייב נמי
משום תינוק? v'lichayav nami mishum tinok? Why aren't you חייב chayav for
the infant? רבא כרבי נתן סבירא ליה. Rava k'Rabbi Noson svira lei.
He'll hold like Rabbi Noson דאמר חי נושא את עצמו. d'amar chai
nosei es atzmo. A live person when you carry them, you're not
חייב chayav for carrying them because they're like carrying themselves.
So the גמרא, it has to
be at least that they can crawl around then, right? Well, that's
the question about do they have to be able to walk and
whatever? It's a discussion that תוספות Tosafot has, but right. וליבטל כיס
לגבי תינוק? v'libatel kis l'gabe tinok? Now here's the reason we're discussing
this. Why isn't the money pouch considered to be secondary to the
infant? ומי לא תנן, umi lo tnan, did we not teach in
our משנה, and now we see why
we're bringing this, המוציא את החי במיטה פטור אף על המיטה. hamotzi
es hachai b'mitah patur af al hamitah. If you take out a
live person in a bed, you're exempt even on the bed, right?
שהמיטה טפילה לו, shehamitah tfeilah lo, because the bed is secondary. And
fundamentally we say you're taking out the person, not the bed, and
the bed is just considered connected to the person. So if you're
exempt on the person, you're exempt on the bed. So the גמרא
says מיטה לגבי חי מבטלי ליה. mitah l'gabe chai mivtali lei.
So the bed for a live person you negate it, meaning it's
like it's there just to serve this person and is completely secondary.
כיס לגבי תינוק לא מבטלי ליה. kis l'gabe tinok lo mivtali lei.
But if you have your money pouch around your kid's neck, it's
like you're
also thinking about that money pouch independently. It's not there just for
the kid, you know, to be somehow like clothing on the kid.
You'll be exempt on the kid's clothes but you're not exempt on
this money pouch. That remains independent.
So it makes them like carrying it?
Right, presumably. Although it would be interesting, let's say it's the kid's
own money pouch, you know, then it's like something like he's carrying.
But here it's like presumably more of your money pouch, so it
seems to be at least the way רש״י Rashi describes it. Okay.
תינוק מת וכיס תלוי לו בצווארו פטור. tinok meys v'kis taluy lo
b'tzavaro patur. So in that case you're פטור patur if the infant
is dead. וליחייב משום תינוק? v'lichayav mishum tinok? Why aren't you חייב
chayav for the infant? So רבא כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה Rava k'Rabbi
Shimon svira lei דאמר כל מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה פטור עליה. d'amar
kol melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufo patur aleha. Since you don't need it
for its own purpose, you're פטור patur on it. Again, why is
it מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufo? One reason רש״י
Rashi says is you wish this case never would have happened, but
that's like a very bizarre definition of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha
she'eino tzricha l'gufo. The easier explanation is you're not trying to bring
it to a particular place, just get the dead infant out of
the house. It doesn't discuss why the כיס kis? is different. Maybe
it's more בטל batel to the infant, what רש״י Rashi says, or
that's also מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufo. Now we've
explained that whole thing, now we talk about why we brought it
in here. Because our משנה seems that the thing that somebody a
baby is carrying or a kid is carrying is considered secondary to
the kid even though it's not clothing, it's not something they're sleeping
on, and so on. So the גמרא says תנן נוטל אדם את
בנו ואבן בידו. tnan motel adam es bno v'even b'yado. So how
does that work? How does...
why is the... why is it considered that you are not moving
the stone? Why is that different than the כיס? kis Now it
assumes that the same definitions would apply whether it's a question of
carrying
by רשות הרבים reshus harabim or a question of moving by מוקצה.
You might have wanted to make a distinction, you know, how you
define the act that you're doing, but the גמרא assumes you can
make that comparison. So why there is it not a problem of
moving and here it is considered a problem? So אמרי דבי רבי
ינאי, amri d'vei Rabbi Yannai, they say in the house of Rabbi
Yannai, בתינוק שיש לו געגועין על אביו. b'tinok sheyesh lo ga'agu'in al
aviv. Technically it really is a problem. It really would be like
you're moving the stone. Again, the reason the כיס is independent is
not because it has money and it's important, it's just because it's
not בטל batel to the infant. Something you're wearing is בטל batel
to you. The bed you're sleeping on is בטל batel to you.
It's there sort of serving you. This thing is like just an
independent thing that maybe you're using, but it's not בטל batel to
you. Okay, so why is once if that's conceptually how we think
about it by carrying and therefore we should conceptually think about it
that way by moving and מוקצה, why isn't it considered here that
you... Are moving the stone and you're moving מוקצה, and the גמרא's
first answer is, okay, you are moving the stone, you are moving
מוקצה, it is an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabonon, but your kid really
has yearnings for you, and if you don't pick him up, he's
going to be emotionally distraught, so we'll allow you to transgress the
prohibition of מוקצה for this because that sort of puts him in
the category of חולה. choleh. Okay, that seems to be a really
weak answer because you're going to have to now deal with the
rest of with the other cases as well, but we will see,
we will continue with this whole issue as we continue tomorrow.